welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right hello everyone and welcome to
the stoy the stoah is a digital campfire
where we gather to go here and dialogue
at the knife's edge of what matters most
I'm Raven and I'll be your host for the
evening today we are joining we are
doing our kickoff of an event that will
be recurring into the future with Sam
Oberg called live players Sam OH is a
research fellow at the long now
foundation and the founder of this mark
analysis he's a writer and speaker and
he's known for his work on intellectual
dark matter and great founder theory and
much more so the way that this event is
gonna go is we'll have 20 minutes of a
disc talk with Sam oh and then we'll
move into the QA if you have a question
for Sam oh you can go ahead and type it
into the chat and then I will emcee the
Q&A period and with that I give you Sam
oh thank you for the introduction Raven
pleasure to be back here I've done
previously a talk on great founder
theory and look forward to discussing
life players with everyone today
this is a start of something of a series
because it's not just a theoretical
concept right
live players are people who in fact are
still shaping our world so there's
always something to talk about in this
regard and there mini-sub ways in which
adaptive individuals shape the world
let's first think of some people who you
know might be good examples of live
players one of my favorite examples are
is Elon Musk he was recently in the news
this Wednesday he's an example of
someone who took two completely failing
industries in a way aerospace and car
manufacturing and actually pushed him
forward into something relatively new or
even completely new this was just
basically something that wasn't supposed
to happen and wasn't going to happen and
in fact almost every bureaucratic
institution stood in his way right
including his nominal clients it's a
NASA let alone his competitors at Boeing
and later on possibly compared
who are as live as he is such as Bezos
most people in the world operate off of
scripts they operate off of what has
worked before what they've observed and
been socialized works for other people
because of that it's best to model human
behavior as exploring these different
ecological niches right so a bird
doesn't know how to fly it knows how to
fly but it doesn't know how the
aerodynamics works and a bird certainly
couldn't design another bird and a bird
certainly can't really learn how to swim
it might through many you know dozens of
generations hundreds of generations
millions of generations evolved into a
duck or a penguin or something like this
but it's never going to do this valley
crossing on its own in a single lifetime
this is precisely what life players do
when I analyze you know basically these
exceptional individuals we always look
for the signs of someone mastering more
than one domain especially if this
domain is completely disconnected from
previous domains right something that
we're someone that historically might
have shown you know small a strong
predisposition towards intelligence work
ends up also being a good general or
someone that had previously run
entrepreneurial ventures suddenly turns
out to be an exceptional artist in their
own right or someone that was once an
exceptional artist ends up being a
politician an interesting example here
is Arnold Schwarzenegger who might seem
like a very trivial example but consider
how many people would in the course of
their life be and you know missing
missing soldier who doesn't show up to
the right appointment because they're
doing a bodybuilder competition and then
manages to talk themselves out of a
disciplinary inquiry by arguing that him
winning the bodybuilding competition is
good PR for his military unit he did
that in Austria that's how he got his
start and after that would pivot this
into appearing in a documentary but it
wouldn't stop there would be an actor
now of course once he became an actor
people constantly kept saying he's not
really an actor
is just a mountain of muscle he just
appears on screen now when he ran for
when he ran to be governor of California
that's when they started calling him an
actor right didn't dismiss him as a
politician you can really dismiss him as
a bodybuilder he'd have to dismiss him
as an actor in each of these cases there
was like some transfer of skill
obviously right like physical and so on
and there was always this thread of
charisma and persuasiveness that he had
but very importantly he was able to
reinvent himself over and over and over
again and I'm quite sure where the
Constitution of the u.s. Buckley
different he'd probably be president
today being foreign-born being Austrian
born he never could run someone like
Howard Hughes was once was once very
similar right he's the less well-known
industrialist predecessor to Elon Musk
arguably maybe inspired Elon Musk or
whatever he was active in the 30s and
40s both in aerospace and in the movies
and movie industry right both of them at
the time high tech frontiers a different
example perhaps one that's you know more
infamous more negative of a live player
would I think be Vladimir Putin right he
starts off as a KGB agent becomes an
assistant to a mayor becomes an
assistant to a president becomes
president stays president or prime
minister for 20 to 30 years while
competing with some of the most ruthless
oligarchs organized crime age organized
crime leaders and yes other KGB agents
for power in the Russian state and
Russia today for whatever you might
think of it punches way above its weight
in terms of its political political
significance this is a country that has
you know 130 million people right now
that has a vast nuclear arsenal but a
GDP that's like smaller than Italy's
days this is a country that is outspent
by the US by an order of 20 possibly 30
depending on how you count it still wins
the proxy Civil War that the US and
Russians were fighting in Syria right
the US government
or at least part of the US government
trying to topple Assad the Russians
trying to support Assad you know of
course the normal way we're talked we
hear about this the way it's talked is
that you know the revolution in Syria
failed well you know who made the
revolution in Syria happen I'm sure
there are many people in Syria that have
deep grievances with Assad and I'm sure
there are many people in Syria who would
have even deeper Grippit grievances with
Isis who's the mean opposition to Assad
right the foreign support be it the
aircraft the anti-aircraft weapons with
the money the intelligence agents the
Special Forces and various military
units such as Russia as a bogner group
or on the US side the equivalent the
equivalent of Blackwater right so these
private military corporations that have
former veterans former soldiers acting
in a private capacity but often still at
the behest of foreign leaders these
resources are the ones that make that
start or end a civil war in reality
right it's usually not inherent to the
country civil war usually has origin
from great power competition coming from
the outside one could even argue that
the American Civil War sorry the
American Revolutionary War
was significantly enabled by French
support and possibly wouldn't have been
possible without French support against
the British he keeps winning this cheese
chess games over and over again against
very different leaders now you might
think that he's completely powerless
with regard to China that Russia is
completely dependent on China however I
recommend you look at the long game he
is selling as much weaponry to India as
he is to China
so all those advanced Russian fighters
that they're selling off to China right
now with the Chinese build off their own
knockoff versions and the Russian
rockets that the Chinese used to fly
people into orbit of course you know
until this Saturday Americans are also
flying their people on to orbit on
Russian Rockets they are also selling
the same to India and if you think about
it there's really no reason to expect
India to be able to afford the same
price
the China can so why is that done he has
also been invited by Russia into some of
these cooperative organizations that
involve both Russia and China what's
happening is that Putin is in the long
term trying to balance China with India
in this regard is way more agile than
the u.s. even though the US should be in
a vastly better that's the stronger
position to prop up India to be let's
say if or generous to Modi a democratic
counterbalance to an authoritarian China
or for being realistic the counterweight
on the Asian continent a country that
has in fact a strong interest in making
sure Southeast Asia is not permanently
dominated by China the ability to infer
things about geopolitics right the
ability to figure out what the right
game to play in geopolitics is that's
kind of easy the hard part is really
implementing it how do you get several
unaccountable intelligence agencies your
military contractors your own diplomats
to play long that's a significant
challenge in coordination because of
this I think almost all great statesmen
are live players now not all great
statesmen great industrialists great
artists are just because they're live
players also great founders here I want
to introduce a distinction between a
founder a great founder in the sense and
a life player Putin didn't create Russia
right nor did he create even the Russian
state ilan I think did obviously create
SpaceX pretty straightforwardly
depending on its success he might well
be remembered or might turn out to have
been a great founder all along or he
might just be a founder right merely
creating a particular company is usually
not enough it really has to be
civilization scale if we colonize Mars
and it's on SpaceX time and on SpaceX
Rockets then I very happily and easily
give him a great founder title because
he makes human civilization
multiplanetary right if SpaceX is just a
moderately successful US aerospace
company I think it's possibly a great
achievement but you know probably not
quite worth this this history altering
perspective of okay this person did
and social engineering to alter the
course of human history right
I do think Elon aspires to it because
SpaceX itself started as this effort to
put a greenhouse on Mars yeah a plant
like a potted plant on Mars what could
be more useless except it's not right
it's art he's in fact a misunderstood
artist and was all along he understands
that the sight of life on another planet
Earth based life not you know not little
green men but earth-based life on the
other planet changes ideology forever
just as the photo of the Earth from the
moon inspired the generation of
environmentalists gave rise to all sorts
of organizations like you know Whole
Earth Catalog was boosted by it one of
my titles from the long now foundation
in a way the long now foundation would
have never happened without the Whole
Earth Catalog and Stewart Franzen but
Elon was trying to do this in the 90s
with Russia and you know he was trying
to buy Russian ICBMs and Russian Rockets
and the Russians weren't taking him
seriously it was a ludicrous proposal so
he said you know I'll build my own which
is seemed an even more ludicrous
proposal right he is trying to get a
colony of people on Mars just change our
self conception as as as as a species he
certainly knows that 300 or 500 or 5,000
people on Mars are going to be
economically irrelevant for the rest of
our lives
none of us is going to see an
economically important Mars but you know
there is a place in the night sky where
people live it'll be something you can
point at and the expectation of how the
future goes will be different it won't
any more be seem insane to propose you
know maybe going to mine asteroids and
also you know the perspective of what's
a planetary disaster and what kills all
of us that's going to change massively
as well the interesting thing about this
is the social engineering is even
evident and the way he approached
promoting his own company right you
could use a boring test Wade satellite
to test your rockets but I mean he
wanted to test the Falcon heavy rocket
he used a sports car you know in that
sports car was a dummy dressed in an
astronaut suit that astronauts who'd
looked very much like a Formula One
uniform this sort of like suit that the
racecar drivers had he had that spunk
planned out for years it was probably
one of the key considerations he had
when the space suit was being designed
and in fact it looks almost identical to
the space suit the astronauts are gonna
be flying in this Saturday how different
is this from NASA style these aren't
like NASA's astronauts these are alongs
astronauts right they're gonna drive
there in the Tesla they're gonna go up
there on the rocket they're probably
gonna even have a shot where they repeat
some of the same dumb jokes as they had
from the car right like the music that
was playing in the car or the towel that
was a reference to the Hitchhiker's
Guide to the galaxy and the social
engineering of that I discuss in a piece
that I rode how Ilyn musk is making
engineers cool again by making the
company's most visible stunts
so obviously cater to the engineers
inside of SpaceX means that within
SpaceX the engineers rather than the PR
people are listened to because the PR
people see that the engineers tastes are
the ones that matter right and basically
he has single-handedly made NASA cool
again NASA might not really like him why
because he's basically bypassing massive
amounts of jobs programs for them but
their entire budget is based on this
kind of coolness in popularity right
he's the one that's replacing 1999 NASA
you know CGI of people on Mars with
cool-looking rockets at Cape Canaveral
right he's doing that not NASA not
Boeing the status of the Nerds and the
engineers mattering means that when
there's an engineering meeting within
SpaceX the Nerds aren't overruled or
bypassed this means that he still
probably occasionally has to smack down
a nerd because engineers have a problem
where they want to build cool toys
instead of being building economic
productive stuff and he probably has his
eye on the economics but he doesn't have
to deal with middle management the way
you might at a different company I think
Google has for example messed us up I
think in Google very slightly rebranded
middle managers are the ones in charge
it's not the truly excellent programmers
and I think if you try to build
something interesting creative
culturally impactful it's not clear this
is good for your position within the
company Amazon has been you know I can
contrast it again but it went really
deeply in tail long because I wanted to
show how an industrialist might not just
through technology but through social
engineering change a whole civilization
first off reviving the cult of the
engineer having the engineers matter
more than the middle managers reviving
the cult of the individual with the
vision and producing essentially a
living artwork on Mars for the purpose
of changing our perspective of who we
are as a species just to say you know
the original picture from the moon that
did something like this the next one on
say a different example of a live player
would be Erik Prince Erik Prince was the
founder of a company called Blackwater
it's been since renamed it's a private
military corporation and very quickly we
realized that he's like an individual
it's managed to get away with feuding
with the US government right like after
having a significant loss of a contract
where those in some scandal I think
there was some substance to the scandal
actually of his his mercenaries doing
some some shitty things in Iraq he lost
a big contract lost a lot of money and
now just occasionally those mercenary
gigs for the Chinese and the Saudis just
they're in Africa in Sudan or wherever
else he's also quite public about his
feud with the US government and his
personal ideology is Randian right it's
a strange mix of Randian ISM and
conservative Christianity just taking
really far and really seriously much as
you could see Elon Musk is taking an
ideology of like old-school 1950 science
fiction way too
thing way too far and just as you might
think of Vladimir Putin taking Russian
patriotism and the idea that at all
costs Russia might stay a great power
much too far nearly all the live players
have this in common their private
ideologies are very weird they are
different from masks consumed beliefs
why because they see more than everyone
else the idea of spontaneous market
derived order certainly is not going to
appeal on appeal that deeply to the
elands of the world maybe a sort of
libertarian aesthetic of well the
shareholders don't tell me what to do I
get to smoke weed on Joe Rogan if I want
to maybe that appeals to him right and
to Putin the idea that there's an
inevitable course of history that leads
to western Atlantic US dominance
international institutions that's
unthinkable it's ludicrous
now even if it's true right even if it's
popular among Russia's technocratic
elites in fact had a lot of difficulty
hiring a US a Russian Minister of
Finance who doesn't basically implicitly
believe in the new liberal future their
ideologies are strange and unique and
some of these life players try to
precise their ideologies try to spread
them for for some other life players
these ideologies are private beliefs
they don't try to spread them they just
act on them so at this point I'm going
to open up for some questions live
players to repeat focus on their
adaptability just because they're
adaptive doesn't mean they create new
institutions even if they create new
institutions unless they impact the
level of a civilization they're not
great founders and a great founder
theory of approach they have strange
unusual private ideologies they jump
industries easily and often they
reinvent themselves through the through
the process and they're deeply
misunderstood by the public which is why
I think agency human agency is
systemically discounted because if
you're very intelligent you try to hide
your agency from the world you don't
want to provoke your adversaries right
for a while you want to be you know the
close advisor to the mayor of st.
Petersburg and then the President of
Russia you don't
necessarily want to be present to brush
on day one so opening this up for for
questions great I'll just warm everybody
up so yeah if you want to throw your
question in the chat and then I will
just call on you and you can ask your
question to Sam Oh
so initial exam oh so you're bringing up
this idea of live players do you have a
contrasting definition of like what a
dead player would be oh yeah a dead
player is anyone that's acting off a
script now again the script might be
very adaptive but it's only adaptive
until it isn't one way to think of this
is that you know the British colonial
office was largest in the 1960 is one
year before its abolition because it was
no longer needed so the colonial office
had the most employees but largest
budget when Britain had the fewest
colonies a different example might be a
company like Ford Motors today write
Ford right no one expects them to build
a self-driving car known even expects
them to build a good electric car heck
we barely expect them to still be
building cars we assume that China is
building those the old-style ones but
you know on paper the company still does
okay
different one might have been the
airline industry the airline industry
had very thin margins these massive
bureaucratic machines trying to you know
optimize every dollar out of passengers
on these very thin margins that enabled
air travel and economies of scale I
think most politicians most CEOs right
now are dead players I really hesitate
to name people who I think are clearly
dead players because this could be seen
as an attack rather there's an
observation it's best to flatter and to
damn by omission yeah all right let's
turn to the chat so Rachel would you
like to ask your question hi Simone my
question is to you Rachel
all right yeah I love the beauty on my
question is about engineers that are
really great founders but they have
these visions for products that you just
know you can't launch is there
specific way that you would recommend
for fine-tuning them if they're talented
enough to have the ground vision if they
continue to like want to produce things
that aren't economically viable how do
you strategize that it's a very
difficult question I think it depends to
a significant amount on the engineer I
think if you get a good sense for the
engineer for what they find as a fun
problem and you kind of find the product
and then and then you talk to them about
a fun problem they could solve that just
happens to be technically very difficult
and necessary for your product I think
that works super well so you might
actually need a team of a super talented
engineer that solves a concrete
difficult problem and a less talented
engineer you just kind of direct them
the right way another way is to try to
educate the engineer about people this
is more difficult but I actually think
this is you know people know about the
negative part of the relationship Steve
Jobs had what his technical partner but
what they don't know is that the
positive end of it was he would find all
these ingenious way to in ways to
communicate things about people right
there's this like very classic story
well you know can you shave off time off
of you know how long it takes for the
machine to boot up and the person says
you know no I can't do that and they're
like well if someone's life depended on
it could you do it
and he says obviously yes I was trying
to do something and then he comes back
with a calculation of the number of
users second save and it turned out to
be something like five to ten human
lifetimes like pool games or cards they
can solve to get them to do specific
time next oh because I think a little
bit disconnected disembodied right they
care about people they just don't know
evilly to think about people first they
think about new systems first cool
excellent
Jacob I don't is this a question that
you want to bring forth or just a idea I
don't know it was a pretty good question
but this will move on Jake if you want
to ask it later I'll just call on you
later just let me know Alan do you want
to ask your question yeah sure so really
interesting topic kind of been thinking
about it a lot recently my question is
you know you mentioned live players that
are currently within the existing
political establishment or structure
whether that's on a national scale or
international scale there's also these
live players that are kind of outside of
it you know whether they're Jeff Bezos
or Elon Musk these founders that have
kind of these really wild ambitions and
aspirations and it seems like in the
past years there's been kind of a meme
of you know Jeff Bezos taking over and
kind of he everyone's gonna be living
under either Amazon or Apple you know
that's gonna be your citizenship rather
than the United States or Russia how do
you see the next I don't know 5 10 15
years playing out with the live players
that are within the existing political
structure and those outside of it and
and the threat that it that it poses for
those within it well I think our
political structure right now is
significantly bereft of life players
right I think we have a lot of people
that were very used to things behaving
in this super predictable super
bureaucratic way and they find it deeply
upsetting when the bureaucracies either
stop working or don't connect to the
world I think it's super telling no
matter who was the president that the
CDC and the FDA could not in fact adapt
in an agile way to code right and I
think that we can you in fact have
systemically been selecting against live
players getting an easy start on their
career right if you alter someone's
first 10 or 20 years you really alter
their entire life the reason Caesar wept
when he was 30 at the statue of
Alexander was partially because you know
user wasn't born king of masa dough you
know the heir to the kingdom of
Macedonia the way Alexander was so of
course Alexander by the time he's 30
conquers the known world and Caesar his
you know barely really started his
political career right he has to play
catch-up now imagine you made it so much
worse but you need to basically for
example for your thoughts to be taken
seriously did you have to play 20 to 30
years of bureaucratic academic games
where you only make sure that you say
small things easily defendable things if
you ever see a big thing you've stepped
onto too many toes this could just be
soul-crushing hang on who's a real-life
player right or if they could stand it
it would've at least be 30 lost years or
20 or 10 lost years and then once you
get tenure you're not safe anyway right
because there's such Academical resupply
i could apply the same logic that i just
applied to academia to say the corporate
career ladder or the kind of the self
promotion game all of this stuff has
been really really wrung out and i'll
link another article i wrote on this you
might enjoy called noyon soar mageddon
which i wrote a few months ago and i
made the unfortunate and unfortunately
correct prediction that there would be
tens of thousands of americans dead by
now and you know of course i originally
wrote hundreds of thousands but was
talked away was talked to my tone it
down right turn down the prediction it's
still in about the right ballpark you
know a hundred thousand isn't isn't too
far away from a few tens of thousands
and in it i advocate that you kind of
have to give keys to the ignition to a
weirdo every now and then i'm gonna give
one that i don't necessarily agree with
dominic cummings right dominic cummings
is a live player and he's been
absolutely hated by british media right
and it's not an accident he's absolutely
hated by british media his job ad if you
read it basically completely disregards
what should be normal chains of
promotion and just asks what for the
smart people to come and work with him
and of course like you know the whole
british establishment is like you can't
just bypass our credentialing system
you can't just bypass our career tracks
and we'll see whether he wins or not in
that regard so I think in the u.s. it's
almost hard to think of a young life
player in the US politics has been an
old people's game for so long that no
matter who becomes president this year
it's gonna be the oldest u.s. president
ever right and Congress has been getting
older every year and the top people in
the civil service have been getting
older and the CEOs of Fortune 500
companies and the board members have
been getting older so I think in the
u.s. at least there's very little
openness there I think it will
eventually reopen and I hope not
catastrophically right because if you
have a super automated system no live
players in it it runs for a long time by
the time live player gets in they might
be like Gorbachev in the Soviet Union
they can only just turn the lights off
and declare defeat cool I hope I
answered your question Alan great Sean
would you like to ask a question
Sanna how do we pronounce your last name
by the way I've heard it's buti'm well
yeah um my question is it's about
weirdness something-something connected
for me when you said that all these live
players have very weird private
ideologies I wonder if you can just
unpack that a little bit is it just that
by definition normalcy within like a
collapsing civilization is just anything
that gets out of that she's gonna be
weird I was mourning if you can unpack
then well can I ask where where do you
think our sense of normal comes from who
creates it I think normalcy is
constructed right so anyone outside the
construct of normalcy is gonna be weird
by definition from a perspective of
normalcy until they create a new normal
I think a very interesting thing to
consider is there's a what's-her-name we
just find her okay Alexandra I'll by
Cohn
I think I'm pronouncing her name right
she's the creator of SCI hub has anyone
here used SCI hub I'm just gonna say I
obviously used it
you should pirate papers just destroy
Elsevier like scatter its ashes among
the like fields to fertilize new science
it should just be destroyed so do you
know what her private ideology is it's
it's a mixture of she literally has an
essay titled why Stalin is God and you
might think that you know she's kidding
for a while until you realized that no
no no she means it quite literally let
me see if I can find this essay if
someone else finds it first there we go
okay I'll link idli let's see what does
she say ideas no copyright about I'll
find I'll find the link later I found a
link it later but she just writes this
massive long essing Russian you have to
put it to Google Translate and turns out
her beliefs about the world they are
derived from a idiosyncratic
interpretation of neuroscience where she
wants all of humanity to together become
one collective brain and she sees all
impediments to sharing information and
knowledge as impeding that brain and
global consciousness and he also she
also believes that Soviet Communism and
some religious communities were the
closest we ever came to that in the past
so we can I think I can probably I
should probably substantiate this as
soon as I can because it just sounds so
insane people and I think I'm making it
up but reality is actually full it's
full of these kind of insanities that
you know just don't fit our normal
worldview right like why hoard people
that go out of their way to alter
reality I think it's you know I think
it's people who don't fit into normal
reality very well and here is the essay
she doesn't make it easy to find there
we go
I almost called it's like esoteric
Stalinism or something you can translate
parts of it and also go to her main site
it has amazing energy it has big
programmer energy
so there we are cool
it's a weirdness partially because our
sense of normalcy is constructed
partially because the people are misfits
they they were round and they were
pressed into you know square pegs
and it just didn't work out for them
like Alexandra tried to make advances in
neuroscience directly but she couldn't
right she had to pivot into linguistics
if you read her bio biography and her
terminology is super weird and
idiosyncratic right like if we unpack
what she means by God and what she means
by what his talents position at the head
of the Communist Party it probably would
end up being something reasonable right
or not awesome great and I'm gonna ask
this question on behalf of Evelyn my
definition our live players appear
category or our live players and dead
players like poles between MIT which
most people fall they're poles but I
think it's sort of it's a bimodal
distribution and it's very heavily
skewed towards dead players so dead here
means strategically dead it doesn't mean
physically dead you can enjoy and live a
very nice life following scripts
following routines it can be experience
rich it's certainly valuable but from a
strategic perspective imagine you're
playing the equivalent of a video game
or a multi-sided board game and you look
around the table and you see okay at
that part of the table there's no human
there's just a piece of paper with some
basic instructions and if and then
clauses and there's only one or two
other people sitting at the table you
know that that game only has two or
three live players and the live players
you know they don't necessarily agree
with each other and I also believe it's
possible to lose hope at one point in
life so it is possible to just become a
dead player or awaken from being a dead
player to becoming a live player but
prepare yourself for things becoming
very strange if you do very quickly
consensus reality starts 10 you know it
starts falling apart right so deeply
bimodal
it is a spectrum I think stepping out of
consensus is a strong attractor I think
stepping into consensus is a strong
attractor just psychologically but also
information theory wise right if you
rely on normal channels of information
you become more normal over time even if
your original at first if you rely on
abnormal channels of information you
become more more distinct more unusual
great thank you
Coleman would you like to ask a question
yeah hey I liked it I like the concept
and I've definitely seen it where I feel
like I can kind of predict their
reaction to certain things but my
question is if there any particular like
impressive case studies have a live
player like moves that you found
particularly inspiring or interesting I
mean there are lots of people um I think
that if you you know if you go read
about Paul Kagame I find him someone
inspiring right where he stabilized the
country that had gone through genocide
and achieved not just prosperity but
reconciliation between the Tutsi and
Hutu right so he's a contemporary life
player
I think historical case studies lots of
them I've done lots of them and I'm
afraid you're just gonna have to wait
for more of the stuff to be released my
biggest bottleneck is always writing I'm
a slow cautious writer faster researcher
but had done case studies on historical
life players such as Catherine the Great
and freed rate the grade but also you
know also some some really interesting
people like you know Rosa Luxemburg and
so on right so I think you could choose
biographies of many people I think in
the West you know Churchill is popular
to read about I think that Lincoln is
certainly acceptable but ideally you
read something about someone from a
really different culture or from a
really different environment and ideally
someone who is in as close a position as
you might find yourself in
hope that makes sense like awesome yeah
thank you yeah great and Jen do you want
to ask a question I'm sure I don't think
I can ask it better than I wrote it so
I'm just gonna read out my question what
what unites otherwise very different
live players what's the underlying
factor is it the outcomes they generate
or the method in which they operate I
think it's the method I think the method
is this they display this adaptability
right this adaptability to circumstance
where the circumstance isn't such as own
a new competitor as arisen it's
something like our industry is no longer
irrelevant our industry has gone away or
there's been an economic crash or hey
there's been a global pandemic or
shipping is delayed for six months right
for I am delayed for six months I'm
stuck outside the country I really have
to emphasize that you know it's these
outlier events that often reveal who's
alive and and who's who's dead player
because you will see which institutions
are piloted by the live players because
those are the ones they're going to not
only survive but to thrive under
adversity right I really don't want to
use the term anti fragile here so I'm
I'm just gonna say that I'm not gonna
use that term but that should drive the
intuition of which circumstances reveal
it I think that their commonalities I
would downplay I think there's the
weirdness they're round in a square
world or they're square in a round world
but they don't have much agreement with
each other they do all without exception
need a personal justification for acting
to change the world so if you know if
you're the maid of Orleans you know if
you're Joan of Arc
you might believe that you've been
chosen by God and you're just enacting
God's will if you are you know Eric
Prince you might think that you are a
Randian hero and that this is what
you're doing with your life and of
course it's morally correct for
to act and then you reference back to
all of this if you're value more Putin
you might think that it's your duty as
the president of Russia and so on - like
maintain a stable independent country
and safeguard the interests in the
traditions of the Russian people except
you just actually believe instead of it
having been this kind of surface thing
that you're supposed to believe so
there's a moral justification for action
because interestingly I think people if
they believe it's not their place to act
they don't now of course just because a
belief is there and beat just because
it's strong enough that the person is
life player it doesn't mean it's like
objectively true right it or at least
according to our value systems it might
not be right I certainly don't agree
with everything with gee-gees your pain
right or if Vladimir Putin but I do
think that they find those
justifications very compelling do you
think it's almost necessary then there's
an element of delusion or irrationality
yeah there is an element of delusion or
irrationality but I think this is this
is the destiny and I think all of us
right like we are incomplete Minds I
think we're much more competent Minds
than we usually think we are I moved
over the years very much away from the
rationalist conception of you know human
minds is inherently broken or like
flawed or biased I think that with
self-examination and reflection but not
just self-examination like work on
difficult problems I think human minds
can become super super impressive super
formidable but I really want to point
out here though that this irrationality
that the live players do is mirrored by
an irrationality of the dead players who
in fact believe that they don't have to
act they believe that they personally
don't have to act it's as much of cope
on the inactive side as it is on the
active side imagine one side has the the
button you know the light is broken and
it always shows green and the other side
has a broken light that always shows red
both of them are disconnected from
reality and we disproportionately
benefit from the few that have the
broken green light
if I could ask a follow-up as well this
is kind of a half form of thought but
let's say this is a new concept for me
and I've learned this from you I wanted
to ask a question about the kind of the
actionability of this like in some sense
is there a survival bias to being a live
player I always think of the exam oh
yeah massive like if you look at a
private equity firm like TPG and you
look at the guy who started it it's like
David Bonderman like was a lawyer doing
Arabic stuff in the Middle East for 12
years and then was in Texas with some
rancher and it's just like so random you
look at the number two guy
ATPG and it's like Baker Scholar Harvard
like partner at Goldman Sachs it's just
like a perfect resume you just think if
you ran that reality again it's kind of
improbable than that first guy would
maybe he would just be some random dude
in the Middle East but that second guy
or maybe maybe he'd be a random dude in
the Middle East or maybe he'd become a
hunger may be he become a Ukrainian
politician or maybe he'd been a Spanish
novelist I'm actually gonna say
something if someone masters several
careers to a high degree consequentially
but gets super improbable right say
Arnold Schwarzenegger being both an
extremely good bodybuilder and running
for governor and succeeding I bet if
Yuri ran history all over again from
Arnold Schwarzenegger is birth he might
become president of Austria he might
become a head of a technological
entrepreneur entrepreneur he might
become a technological entrepreneur he
might become the head of a mercenary
outfit or he might become a Hollywood
actor all over again right meanwhile I
think that if he ran the universe where
the person that you know has the super
nice sounding cookie cutter standard
career you know you rerun that person's
career in a different world I think
there's still a very high grade
careerist but they ultimately are
climbing ladders they're not building
ladders right to climbing someone else's
ladder someone else designed that career
track for them it wasn't it's not
objective right Harvard's not objective
the career tracks are not objective
they're arbitrary at their very best
they can be the equivalent to the roman
courses on Arum which is the sequence of
posts you make people go through to show
their worth but the exact obstacle
course is super arbitrary right and
super contingent yeah so that's what
that's what I always say right and and
note when you rerun the universe does
that person really out-compete other
people who are super similar maybe that
super standard cookie cutter career is
also improbably that person to get at
the end of the cookie cutter career had
to out-compete a thousand or ten
thousand or fifty thousand people trying
to do a cookie cutter career the live
player only need to out-compete no two
three people maybe so if I'm if I could
paraphrase what I'm getting from you
this live player concept isn't
necessarily only helpful as an analysis
tool it's potentially helpful also as
like a personal action tool it could
give you extra confidence if you are
different we're the costume dead being
welding like that you killed like like
literally Soviet dissidents right there
were life players right or it might you
might you might become a billionaire or
something and or you might end up being
a writer who's recognized after your
time and just look like a miserable
until that right so what's the
difference between being a live player
and simply going for higher risk higher
reward I mean I always think of that Joe
Hinrich thing like tradition is smarter
than you like most of the time when you
question tradition you like the base
rate is you're going to be wrong there
is a lot of accumulated wisdom in
tradition so what's the difference there
it's very difficult to describe from the
inside but super apparent that some
people routinely outperform tradition
well I think I think what they actually
do is they understand the reason the
tradition was there in the first place
Chesterton spends write the argument of
Chester turns fence applies for a fence
that you don't know the purpose of if
you know exactly who and why put the
fence there and then of course you can
safely take it down when those
circumstances are or matched and I think
that you
it's very difficult to get there I think
principles include original thought with
openness to unusual information channels
involve developing some charisma while
being kind of either a social or mildly
antisocial something's going wrong
because I think that connection is like
heroin for people right they love being
close to other individuals and if it
means smothering over awkward ideas to
be so close to others I think this is
human nature that we do this so it says
if you actually think I'm flipping the
usual sheep thing on its head usually
it's a complain that he of humans are
sheep this is bad they're just cowardly
I actually think it might be this desire
to be so close to other minds that so
it's the love that causes people to be
all the same so I actually think it's
probably coming from a positive not from
a negative impulse though fear can also
be used to like tamp down variation but
I think most of the lack of variation
that we see this kind of clustering and
human distributions I think that's
because of our desire for connection
essentially right people sometimes want
to be great writers because they want to
be closer in spirit to the writer that
greatly inspired them right so it can be
also an inspiration to be an outlier so
if I have something it's like you know
develop deep empathy that doesn't
overlook flaws to these unusual
exceptional people and perhaps you know
even if you don't want to be one
consider helping one or finding one
right the the self-interested Randian
angle on this might be you know you
don't have to take all the risks you can
just help someone else's risk you know
have a better risk/reward payoff have
their payoff curve be slightly higher
and take your share you know the
equivalent of VC VC of humans or
something though I've got please let's
not point that as a term for Twitter
BIOS god awesome so let's go back to the
chat here Thank You ang and those are
great questions I wanted to do Tyson's
question because it's really fun
someplace and do an ask your question
gerrae thanks Raven sorry I don't think
I'm hearing you yeah you're muted thank
you so much my bad
all right my question is what are some
strange outlandish or eccentric skills
that live players of the future are
starting to learn and study today well
you know the crucial the crucial thing
here is that I think it's going to be
very different I think one of the things
that's probably happening right now is
that people who have reinvented by
accident at least the scientific method
that is people who know how to set up
theories and set up experiments on the
basis of theories they have a strong
advantage right now because their
society is overloaded with scientism and
essentially fake science but it's fake
science with the Harvard degree attached
to it so you can't call it fake there's
like you know it's I think it's pretty
much damning for example the use of
statistics in medicine right or the
recent replication crisis we are as a
society cargo cult informal methods on a
truly massive scale because we you know
we demanded that there be a massive
expansion of scientists after the
Sputnik moment right the launch of
Sputnik in the 1950s and you know much
as the Soviet shoe manufacturer that is
given insufficient leather by the
central planned economy but told to make
20,000 pairs of shoes they make tiny
tiny shoes that are useless because on
paper they fill the quota I think we've
made tiny tiny PhDs to fill the quota
that allows us to claim they were
thriving scientific society right so I
think real science when you can do it
very powerful very important done by
very few people
the second thing is capitalism actually
doing capitalism super rare very
important
this is kind of what Peter teal writes a
lot about this I think he's completely
right I also think doing Marxism for
real actually you know no one's really
done societal analysis plus trying to
organize political parties that have as
their a key objective building new
states like what does the last political
party you remember it's dedicated to
like creating a new socio-economic order
people were so invested in the
Bolsheviks because the Bolsheviks were
the equivalent of like a high IQ cult
when they were founded right that's why
I was so enticing not only do you get a
hang out with your friends and read the
same books your friends have been
reading you get to participate in the
betterment of all of society and that
was super appealing to people who are
sometimes already very well off or not
themselves proletariat and again like
you know I I don't think I don't think
the Bolshevik Revolution made the world
better though I certainly think Vladimir
Lenin is like absolutely a great founder
type character because he invented the
party at the political Revolutionary
Party and the party state and today we
see in China like a live descendant of
that model so I do think that's that's a
big change to society so another one is
the ability to read by which I mean the
ability to read things slowly and think
read things between the lines and try to
extract deep meaning from text and even
at the best of times
I think this level of literacy was never
reached by more than five percent of the
population but I think in the last 40 to
50 years something has happened where
even the five percent is like vastly too
many I think right now it's like maybe
like half a percent or 1 percent it
might've been the rise of visual culture
right that might have been the reason or
it might have been the attention
scrambling effects of mass masley you
know drugging up most of the population
and you know use of the internet I don't
really know I do know for a fact that
people had higher reading comprehension
and because people now have higher lower
reading comprehension the writing has
gotten orders
compared a scientific paper in the most
complex field you can find from 1925 to
a modern scientific paper in the most
trivial field you can find the 1925
paper will be more intelligible and
understandable because it's written for
a person right the modern scientific
paper is usually written for a committee
so it's trying to be defensive it's
trying to be small it's not trying to
convey it's not expecting there's a mind
on the other end that's doing it it's
expecting to be evaluated as homework
the difference between a homework and
research on a deep deep level is unclear
right so I don't mean to be picking on
academia obviously I think there's great
work that sometimes happens in corners
of academia but I'm trying to convey
that there's something deeply wrong with
the way we read and it's very difficult
to convey so maybe that's intellectual
dark matter reading but for real because
believe me if you read books for real
and you act on them you get very weird
very quickly I hope that was a good
answer to your question yeah very good
thank you
excellent we're really winding down here
I don't know if we have time for well
Jacob has a question that is about
success Jacob do you wanna ask a
question and squeeze it in in the last
few minutes sorry I'm sorry I didn't
answer your last so so I guess if my
intuition is that we're putting the cart
before the horse like that we have to
have some sort of relatively
comprehensive unified definition of
success right because for example like
speaking of outlandish I actually don't
think that Elon Musk is a live player I
don't think I actually don't think he's
successful by my by my standard sure
well you know that that's not landish
obviously but that's just a case in
point of don't we have to first exam
little it's not Jeff well I'm not seeing
successful right I'm just saying they go
off script and buy successful I mean
they achieve what they set out to it
right note that for 4life players I
listed people with whose objectives I
disagree so it's not like I think
there's an objective single measure I
think there are multiple possible
agendas people could be pursuing and
what I'm what is looked at here is like
this can really outlier human skill and
outlier human impact so if that feels
more accurate and I think it probably is
we can say outlier impact outlier human
skill rather than success like it's very
happy to substitute those words to avoid
that that's not great and with that I
think we'll have to wrap up here thank
you so much Sam oh and I'm so glad that
you're gonna keep coming because there's
so much rich material here thank you for
having me and I really want to say thank
you through the audience these were
great questions I enjoyed answering them
and also I hope people can tell this is
not scripted I was just trying my best
to live answer the questions and
sometimes you know the reality of things
how simple things are can seem
outlandish so hope everyone has a good
evening great and so I'll just do a
little bit of a shout out for the events
that we have coming up tomorrow
Bonita Roy is doing an event in the
morning this is one of our wisdom gym
events so check that out we also have
earth regeneration with Joe Brewer Joe I
was really doing this amazing work doing
ecosystem regeneration and restoration
and creating all of these different
institutions me he's a live player for
sure so come and hear him talk I think
it'll be really interesting that'll be
at 2 p.m. Eastern time and then I will
be hosting Socratic speed-dating the ask
hole edition so we'll be playing asshole
again this week which is a social
boundary-pushing game and that'll be at
7 p.m. Eastern Time and Tyson do you
want to talk about your event as well
yeah Thank You Raven the event is called
flowing with unknowingness and so we
explore deepening our relationship with
uncertainty through creative
self-expression and the cherry on top is
accessing group flow state that
experience where I
feel that we are each instruments to the
same song and seeing how well we can tap
into that sweet space and yet we
practice freestyle rap and spoken word
exploring language and creative
expression and that is Saturdays at 8
p.m. Eastern and I look forward to
seeing some of you there it's been a lot
of fun awesome and then just to close
off the stove is a gift that we see we
want to give for everyone at this time
of need and if you would like to give us
a gift in return you can visit the stoah
at the gift economy and with that thank
you everyone and have a wonderful
evening